Yella Pessl Papers
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Yella Pessl Papers1918-1979
nam_ger073
This collection documents the musical career of Yella Pessl, a harpsichordist, pianist and organist.
Pessl, Yella, 1906-1991
13 cubic ft.
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Biographical History
Gabriella Pessl Sobotka was a harpsichordist, pianist and organist who performed under the name Yella Pessl. Born in Vienna, she had a musical career in Europe before immigrating to the United States in 1931.
Pessl was best known for her interpretations of Bach and was founder and director of the Bach Circle, a New York group specializing in lesser-known works of Bach and other Baroque composers. Pessl toured extensively in the United States, performing in as a soloist and with orchestras. She also had her own radio program and was on the faculty of Columbia University.
Pessl died at the age of 85 in 1991 in Northhampton, Mass. Her husband, Dr. Harry Sobotka, predeceased her in 1970.
This collection contains Yella Pessl's correspondence, 1930-79; musical manuscripts, arrangements, and fingered sheet music, primarily of the keyboard works of J. S. Bach, undated; scrapbooks pertaining to her concert career, 1924-56; 78 commercial and private recordings of her performances on harpsichord and piano, primarily from the 1940s and 1950s; and printed materials.
The collection also contains 194 12-inch records, 39 10-inch records by Pessl. In addition, there are 50 12-inch records and 16 10-inch records either not by Pessl or unidentifiable.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is not processed. Some boxes are described at the box level. Others are described at the item level.
Acquisition Information
The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives acquired this collection from Yella Pessl-Sobotka 1978
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Pessl, Yella, 1906-1991; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Women musicians; Scores; Correspondence; Clippings; Concert programs; 78 rpm records; Scrapbooks
Container List
- Large navy scrapbook with clippings, programs. Numerous inserts, 1952-1956; nam_ger073-1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Beige scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1946-1947; nam_ger073-2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Large black and gold scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1945; nam_ger073-3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Large brown scrapbook with clippings, 1943-1944; nam_ger073-4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Large brown scrapbook with black design with clippings, programs, 1942; nam_ger073-5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Large manilla folder scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1941; nam_ger073-6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Large black scrapbook with clippings, 1940 July 15 - 1941 February 3; nam_ger073-7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scrapbooks, loose clippings, Undated; nam_ger073-8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Large black scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1940; nam_ger073-9 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Black scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1939; nam_ger073-10 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Clippings in manilla envelope, mainly duplicates of scrapbook clippings., 1938-1939; nam_ger073-11 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Large brown scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1938; nam_ger073-12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Black scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1936-1937; nam_ger073-13 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook with no cover. Clippings, some programs, 1935-1938; nam_ger073-14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Small gray/black mottled scrapbook. Programs, clippings, 1931-1932; nam_ger073-15 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Small brown and tan scrapbook. Clippings, programs. 1924-1935. 60p., nam_ger073-16 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Clippings until 1930. Clippings in brown manilla envelope, 1920s; nam_ger073-17 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous clippings over many years, Undated; nam_ger073-18 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Clippings concerning Yella Pessl, Susanne Bloch and Carl Dolmetsch, 1936 March 17; nam_ger073-19 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous clippings in manilla folder, 1937; nam_ger073-20 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous programs, 1930s-1970s; nam_ger073-21 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Program outlines. Columbia Broadcasting Systems, 1940-1941; nam_ger073-22 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Austrian programs and concert reviews, 1930s; nam_ger073-23 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Bach Circle programs, 1937-1947; nam_ger073-24 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- List of materials in collection, as compiled by Yella Pessl, Undated; nam_ger073-25 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Curriculum vita, autobiographical materials, Undated; nam_ger073-26 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 2 small notebooks, Undated; nam_ger073-27 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous notes, Undated; nam_ger073-28 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Bach Circle correspondence, materials, Undated; nam_ger073-29 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence file J, Undated; nam_ger073-30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence file L, Undated; nam_ger073-31 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence file M, Undated; nam_ger073-32 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, concert season, 1944-1945; nam_ger073-33 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, management, 1946-1947; nam_ger073-34 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1930s-1970s; nam_ger073-35 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Fan mail and other miscellaneous correspondence, 1940s; nam_ger073-36 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Die Schule. Eine Komdie von Jella Pessl dem Vater zu seinem Geburtstag, 1918 November 23; nam_ger073-37 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- An Example of North-American Figured Bass Practices as Illustrated by the Notebook of Amy van Vleck. Also 3 reproductions from the notebook of Amy Van Vleck., Undated; nam_ger073-38 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Articles by Pessl, Undated; nam_ger073-39 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Interview, Undated; nam_ger073-40 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Press book, Undated; nam_ger073-41 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Contracts, Undated; nam_ger073-42 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Photographs of Yella Pessl, some duplicates, Undated; nam_ger073-43 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous offprints, musical subjects, Undated; nam_ger073-44 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Summer resort advertisements, Undated; nam_ger073-45 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous forms, Undated; nam_ger073-46 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous materials, Undated; nam_ger073-47 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Etchings, Undated; nam_ger073-48 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Student papers, Undated; nam_ger073-49 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- [Hyde, Fred]. "Mersenne's Role in the History of the Tempered Tuning of Instruments", Undated; nam_ger073-50 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- [Hyde, Fred]. "Chapter I: Mersenne, The Man; His Life." Also notes, presumably by Pessl, Undated; nam_ger073-51 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous catalogs, Undated; nam_ger073-52 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-53 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-54 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-55 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-56 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-57 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-58 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-59 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-60 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-61 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-62 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-63 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-64 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-65 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-66 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-67 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated; nam_ger073-68 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Scores, reel-to-reel tapes, microfilms, slides, Undated; nam_ger073-69 (Box 21, Folder 1)